Pease family papers SSC.MS.00285
Sophia Smith Collection
Pease family papers
1861-2016
Sophia Smith Collection
SSC.MS.00285
28.5 linear feet (17 boxes. Other materials in the collection: small cardboard box and 2 rolls of diplomas on shelf.)
Jane Hanna Pease (1929-2016) and William Henry Pease (1924-2013) were scholars who published widely on the anti-slavery movement. Jane Pease's research interests also included nineteenth century American social history and antebellum urban history. Henry Pease's research interests included American reform, and American social and intellectual history. Jane Pease graduated from Smith College in 1951 and went on to earn her Ph.D. from the University of Rochester in 1969. She taught history at the Emma Willard School from 1955 to 1964 and at the University of Calgary from 1964 to 1979, when she was appointed professor of history at the University of Maine, Orono. William Pease graduated from Williams College in 1947 and earned his Ph.D. at the University of Rochester in 1955. He taught english and history at the Northfield Mount Herman School from 1948 to 1951 and taught history at the Rensselaer Polytechnical Institute from 1955 to 1964. He taught at the University of Calgary from 1964 to 1968, when he was appointed professor of history at the University of Maine, Orono. His research interests include American reform, and American social and intellectual history. The Pease Family papers contains biographical and genealogical material; personal and professional correspondence; writings and lectures; memorabilia; photographs; teaching materials; and subject files, including research material for the Negro Communities Project. Writings include research materials for several of Jane Pease's books, including Black Utopia and They Who Would be Free.
Biographical Note
Jane Hanna Pease (1929-2016) and William Henry Pease (1924-2013) were scholars who published widely onn the anti-slavery movement. She graduated from Smith College in 1951 and went on to earn her Ph.D. from the University of Rochester in 1969. She taught history at the Emma Willard School from 1955 to 1964 and at the University of Calgary from 1964 to 1979, when she was appointed professor of history at the University of Maine, Orono. Her research interests also included nineteenth century American social history and antebellum urban history. William Henry Pease (1924-2013) researched and wrote on American reform movements and American social and intellectual history. He graduated from Williams College in 1947 and earned his Ph.D. at the University of Rochester in 1955. He taught English and History at the Northfield Mount Herman School from 1948 to 1951 and then taught history at the Rensselaer Polytechnical Institute from 1955 to 1964. He taught at the University of Calgary from 1964 to 1968, when he was appointed professor of history at the University of Maine, Orono.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Related Materials
Books available in 5 College libraries: The Antislavery Argument; Bound with Them in Chains; The Fugitive Slave Law and Anthony Burns; Ladies, Women, and Wenches; They Who Would Be Free
Scope and Contents
The Pease Family papers span the years 1861-1974 and contain biographical and genealogical material, particularly about the Hanna family; personal and professional correspondence; writings and lectures; memorabilia; photographs; teaching materials; and subject files, including research material for the Negro Communities Project. Writings include research materials for several of Jane Pease's books, including Black Utopia and They Who Would be Free. Also included are records of Jane and William Pease's campus committee work.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Pease family papers were donated by Margaret Pease Carels, Barbara Pease Stuart, Jane H. Pease and William H. Pease from 1984 to 2016.
Abolitionists--United States--Biography--Sources; African Americans--Colonization--Sources; Sao Paulo (Brazil)--History--Sources; Smith College--Students--History--Sources; Historians--United States--Biography--Sources; African Americans--History--19th century--Sources; Family--United States--History--Sources; Pease, William H., 1924-; Organization files; Publications; Antislavery movements--United States--History--Sources; Historians -- United States -- Biography -- Sources; Lectures; Pease, E. Jane Hanna; Pease family; Pease, William Henry, 1924-; University of Maine at Orono--History--Sources; Hanna family; Pease, Jane H.
- Jane Hanna Pease and William Henry Pease journals article transcripts, related correspondence and miscellaneous financial materials, 1949-2000; 2002-S-0012; Pease, William and Jane H.; 0.75 linear feet
  - "Traditional Belles or Borderline Bluestockings?" typescript and related correspondence, 2000; 2002-S-0012 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence pertaining to entry in "Encyclopedia of American Cultural and Intellectual History", 1998-2000; 2002-S-0012 (Box 1)
  - "Neither Melanie nor Scarlett: The Petigru Women of the Carolinas" typescript, 1994; 2002-S-0012 (Box 1)
  - Account books and income tax returns, 1949-1999; 2002-S-0012 (Box 1)
- Jane Hanna and William Henry Pease correspondence, appointment books and reviews pertaining to their work, 1984-2004; 2005-S-0057; Pease, E. Jane Hanna; 1 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Pease, E. Jane Hanna
  - Correspondence and deed of gift for donations to various institutions, 1991-1995; 2005-S-0057 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, reviews and notes regarding writings and lectures, 1992-2004; 2005-S-0057 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, reviews and notes regarding writings and lectures, 1995-2003; 2005-S-0057 (Box 2)
  - Personal correspondence, 1984-2004; 2005-S-0057 (Box 2)
  - Appointment books, 1984-2004; 2005-S-0057 (Box 2)
  - Address books, 1950-2000; 2005-S-0057 (Box 2)
- Jane Hanna Pease and William Henry Pease correspondence, 2000-2003; 2005-S-0064
  - Correspondence, 2000-2003; 2005-S-0064 (Box 1)
- Jane Hanna Pease and William Henry Pease personal and professional materials including family biographical information, correspondence and journal articles, 1950-2007; 2009-S-0095; Pease, E. Jane Hanna; 1.25 linear feet (1 box)
  - Appraisal of Maine summer home, 2003; 2009-S-0095 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence regarding Carol Woods Retirement Comunity, 1986-2003; 2009-S-0095 (Box 1)
  - Materials regarding the deaths of Clarence G. Pease and Arline Pease, 1974; 2009-S-0095 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and miscellaneous materials regarding Eva Edgerly, 1985-1993; 2009-S-0095 (Box 1)
  - Jane Pease records regarding cataract surgery, 1984-1990; 2009-S-0095 (Box 1)
  - Real estate sales, maintenance and miscellaneous transactions, 1970-2009; 2009-S-0095 (Box 1)
  - Published journal articles, 1950-2009; 2009-S-0095 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 2004-2007; 2009-S-0095 (Box 1)
- William Pease memoir manuscript, correspondence, CD elegy by Jane H. Pease and miscellaneous materials, 1982-2014; 2002-2014; 2014-S-0055; Pease, E. Jane Hanna; 0.5 linear feet (1 box)
  - "A Brief Memoir", 2008; 2014-S-0055 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 2002-2012; 2014-S-0055 (Box 1)
  - Papers and related correspondence, 2005-2009; 2014-S-0055 (Box 1)
  - "An elegy for Bill (Pease)" by Jane Pease CD, 2014; 2014-S-0055 (Box 1)
- Jane Hanna Pease and William Henry Pease correspondence, family history, research, journals and photographs, 1913-2016; 2016-S-0049; Pease, E. Jane Hanna; 4 linear feet (5 boxes)
  - Personal correspondence, 2007-2016; 2016-S-0049 (Box 1)
  - Professional correspondence, 1961-2011; 2016-S-0049 (Box 1)
  - Legal documents, 2006; 2016-S-0049 (Box 1)
  - Publishing contracts, 1972-2001; 2016-S-0049 (Box 1)
  - Untitled manuscript, undated; 2016-S-0049 (Box 1)
  - Family history materials including correspondence, legal documents, photographs and CD, undated; 2016-S-0049 (Box 1)
  - Jane Pease "Autobiographical Reflections", 1977-2003; 2016-S-0049 (Box 1)
  - Jane Pease journal, 2015; 2016-S-0049 (Box 1)
  - William Pease memoir on two audio CDs, 2008; 2016-S-0049 (Box 1)
  - Professional and miscellaneous correspondence, 1977-2014 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous legal document, 1951-2013; 2016-S-0049 (Box 2)
  - Family photographs, 1940-1959; 2016-S-0049 (Box 2)
  - Jane Pease Smith College honors thesis, 1951; 2016-S-0049 (Box 2)
  - William Pease to Jane Pease correspondence, 1940-1960; 2016-S-0049 (Box 2)
  - Jane Pease travel journals, 1985; 1992; 2016-S-0049 (Box 2)
  - Book contracts, 1962-2008; 2016-S-0049 (Box 2)
  - Jane and William Pease bibliography, 1951-2011; 2016-S-0049 (Box 2)
  - Jane Pease MA thesis, 1957; 2016-S-0049 (Box 2)
  - "Bill - Brief Essays", 2009; 2016-S-0049 (Box 2)
  - William Pease MA thesis, 1948; 2016-S-0049 (Box 3)
  - William Pease PhD dissertation, 1955; 2016-S-0049 (Box 3)
  - Photograph albums, 1913-1969; 2016-S-0049 (Box 4)
  - Unidentified photograph and embroidery, undated; 2016-S-0049 (Box 5)